okay so now that we have seen a detailed
example of how the Rob based processor
Works let's look at a Rob timing example
so this is how we can figure out what
happens when without actually tracking
everything like in the previous very
busy video here we have some
instructions here we have what the
latencies of various units are and now
we're just going to track when
instructions are issued when they begin
executing when do they write the result
broadcast it and when do they commit and
here we will put some comment that kind
of you know help us tell what happened
when and why this time let's make it a
bit different from before first our
processor will free a reservation
station when the result is broadcast not
when we actually dispatch the
instruction uh this can happen for
example because the processor is uh
doing something speculative and it wants
to keep the instruction until it's
really sure that uh you know the
instruction should have executed so some
of the processors actually do this so
let's try an example with this the
processor can still issue capture a
result and dispatch the instruction in
the same cycle but the execution will
again happen in the following cycle this
is just like the previous processors and
again we have the ad take one cycle
multiplication takes 10 cycles and
divide takes 40 Cycles so let's see well
in cycle one we will try to issue the
first instruction and nothing else can
happen because we don't have any other
instructions in the processor this this
instruction of course being the first
one we know that it doesn't depend on
anything so it will begin executing in
the second cycle it's a divide
instruction takes 40 Cycles to do it so
40 Cycles after this one we will try to
write the result and that happens in
cycle 42 and commit will happen in the
following cycle because this is the very
first instruction so we can just say 43
here now let's go to this multiplication
once we have some instructions in the
processor we have to start worrying
about reservation stations and R entries
and so on and we haven't said how many R
entries we have but let's say we have a
lot of R entries however we still have
two divide multiply reservation stations
and three add subtract reservation
stations so now one of our reservation
stations for divide and multiply is busy
between Cycles 1 and
42 there is however another one so this
multiplication can be issued in the
following
cycle so it will issue in cycle two when
can it execute well it uses R5 and R six
this doesn't use R3 so it can actually
execute in the very following cycle so
we will start executing it here takes 10
Cycles so we will broadcast the result
in cycle
13 and when will we commit well we
cannot commit in Cycle 14 now we have to
wait for both the previous instruction
to commit and for us to have a result so
really we will commit in cycle 44 now
let's look at this ad here it's using R7
and R8 so it will be executing right
after IT issues we have add and subtract
reservation stations remember we have
three separate reservation stations for
that so we will issue in cycle three
start execution in cycle 4 takes only
one cycle so we will write the result in
cycle 5 and now when do we commit this
instruction in cycle 45 now Things
become a little bit more interesting
because this multiplication wants to
issue in cycle four remember we are
issuing instructions in order we have
reached this instruction in cycle four
we want to issue it
however we need a multiplication and
divide reservation station for that and
we free reservation stations when we
Broast not when we dispatch in this
processor so we already have since cycle
two both of the reservation stations
used the first available one will become
at cycle 13 so basically only in Cycle
14 we can actually issue this
instruction so this instruction was
waiting to issue but couldn't because
there was no free reservation station
so let's kind of note this so this is
just kind of to note that basically we
have been delayed in our issue because
of the needing the reservation station
we are using results of R1 and R3 so we
have to wait for the multiplication and
add before we can execute but those
results have been broadcast in Cycles 13
and five so in cycle 15 which is when we
can try to execute we can if we manage
to issue in cycle 4 we would still had
to wait until Cycle 14 here because of
cycle 13 here so pretty much our result
would be broadcast in cycle 13 we would
be able to dispatch only in 13 we would
be executing in 14 because we also
needed to wait for a reservation station
we couldn't issue until Cycle 14 so we
can only execute in cycle 15 it's a
multiplication instruction so it's going
to try to broadcast the result in cycle
25 and we will be able to commit it in
cycle 46 now let's look at the subtract
instruction it is going to try to issue
in cycle 15 we have to issue in order so
although we could have issued this
instruction in cycle 4 as far as you
know dependencies are concerned because
we could have issued this instruction in
cycle 345 if everything was okay and
there was a free reservation station at
the time here but remember we have to
issue instructions in order because of
that this will issue in cycle 15 and we
will now grab another reservation
station in the ad subtracting so now
what happens is we need to figure out
when do we execute we need R1 and R5 the
R1 comes from this multiplication the R5
is already available because none of
them are producing it the R1 here
becomes available after this result is
written so in cycle 25 we grab the value
need we need and then in cycle 26 We
Begin executing it's a subtract it's
going to finish in in cycle 27 and it's
going to commit in cycle 47 not because
of this this but because of this and
finally let's look at this ad here it's
going to issue in cycle 16 execution
will begin when R4 and R2 are available
R4 is available in cycle 27 but R2 is
available only in cycle 42 so we will
dispatch in cycle 42 and begin executing
in cycle 43 we will write a result one
cycle after that and we will commit in
cycle
48 and that concludes our discussion now
here you want to make a note for example
that the issue has been delayed because
of reservation stations and for these
instructions for example here you may
want to knowe that execution has been
delayed because of R2 just so that if
you on an exam or something if you
slightly messed this up if you made
these notes at least whoever is grading
this would be able to follow you know
what went wrong and you know what was
your real mistake and what was just the
consequence of that mistake